# 有很多人做干烧都要勾芡
A lot of people add slurry when dry braising
# 这种是错误的
That’s wrong
# 你看现在就能看出来
Now you can see
# 这有粘稠度没有 有
Is the sauce viscous? Yes
# 哪来的
Where does this viscosity come from?
# 肉肉冯 不能光给你肉吃
Meat Eater Feng, I can’t just serve you meat
# 给你一条平鱼 也是鲳鱼
I’ll cook a flatfish for you today, which is a butterfish
# 你看 把这铰了 做鱼要讲整洁
Look, cut this off. Presentation must be neat
# 斜刀一片就开
Slice it open with an angle
# 就这么一点儿提出来
Remove the guts
# 把腮抠出来
And the gills
# 这个鱼你知道好在哪儿么老冯
Do you know what’s so good about this fish, Lao Feng?
# 你知道北方人啊吃鱼比较笨
Northern people are not so good at eating fish
# 怕刺多 所以这个鱼就一条刺
They are afraid of the bones. But this fish has only one large bone
# 这一夹就一块一块 对没错
You pull the fish meat off the bone. Yes, you are right
# 过去我们北方这一带
In the past, around this area in the North
# 就是平鱼 带鱼 黄花鱼
We only had flatfish, beltfish and yellow croaker
# 就这三鱼 别的没什么鱼
Just these three, no other kind of fish
# 怎么打刀呢 就是井字刀呗
How to score the fish? Crosscut
# 这边是这样
On the other side, score it like this
# 知道了吧 它不是两面全是井字
You see, it’s not crosscut on both sides
# 一面柳一面井
One side crosscut, the other side parallel
# 哪面朝上 十字朝上
Which side faces up? The crosscut one
# 这个咱们也得腌
We must marinate the fish as well
# 酒
Cooking wine
# 盐 一勺半
One and half teaspoons of salt
# 花椒粒 大料瓣
Sichuan peppercorns and star anise
# 葱 直接一拍就搁里了
Spring onions. Simply slap them and put them into the bowl
# 因为它要的是汁儿 这是进底味
As we just need the juice to give the fish some base flavour
# 腌二十分钟就可以
Marinate it for 20 minutes
# 我看这块肉不错 一见肉就乐了
This is a very nice piece of pork. You become so happy as soon as you see pork
# 这才叫肉 它香啊
This is what I call MEAT, because it’s so aromatic
# 我给你多搁点肉吧
I’ll add some more pork for you
# 其实按正常来说有这一片就够了
Normally, one slice of pork is enough
# 咱们多来点 一定带皮
Let’s have some more today. Leave the skin on
# 您少吃（肉）多吃鱼让您
You shall eat less pork and more fish
# 我少吃鱼多吃肉啊
And I’ll eat less fish and more pork
# 这肉还真不少 不错不错
That’s a decent amount of pork. Looks great
# 看着就喜兴 过瘾
They look delightful and satisfying
# 姜切菱形
Cut the ginger in diamond shape
# 葱切末
Finely chop some spring onions
# 蒜 这一条鱼就够了
Garlic, this is enough for one fish
# 还有点香菇
Some shiitake mushrooms
# 然后咱们今天应该有点笋
Then we should have bamboo shoots today
# 他买的笋丝
He bought these bamboo shoots
# 但是咱们意思意思啊 借借味
Just a little bit, to add some extra flavours
# 这就行了
That’s it
# 点火烧油 炸鱼
Wok on, oil in, heat up, let’s fry the fish
# 这鱼一定拿纸给擦干
Make sure you pat dry the fish
# 省的崩着你 直接炸
The oil may splatter if just deep-frying the wet fish
# 那咱用油煎也行啊 煎可以啊
We can also pan fry it. Yes, you can
# 但是按正规来说是炸
But the best way is deep frying
# 一过油它香啊
It will be extra aromatic after deep frying
# 你知道炸鱼的油面怎么看吗
Do you know how to check if the oil is ready for frying?
# 你看轻轻的翻滚的时候
When the surface is slightly bubbling
# 它这油温就合适了
It has the right temperature
# 基本上就在七成了
It’s around 70% hot
# 可以了
There we go
# 炸成这样就行了
Fry it until it looks like this
# 能翻个面咱瞧瞧那面么
Could we see the other side?
# 两面金黄
Golden on both sides
# 好 空油
Alright, take it out
# 先下什么 下肥肉膘
What do we add in first? Fatty pork
# 这个菜（煸炒的时候）
When stir frying this
# 不要搁大料 也不搁花椒
Don’t add any star anise or Sichuan peppercorns
# 红烧是搁花椒大料 干辣椒肉片
You add Sichuan peppercorns, star anise, dried chilli and pork slices when you braise things in soy sauce
# 这是川菜的干烧
But this is dry braising in Sichuan Cuisine
# 干烧不需要 对
Dry braising doesn’t need those ingredients. Yes
# 你看 炒出油来
Look, render out the fat
# 搁一点甜面酱
Put in a little bit Tian Mian Jiang (sweet bean paste)
# 完了之后 搁豆瓣酱
Followed by some Dou Ban Jiang (spicy broad bean paste)
# 小火慢炒 放小料头
Sauté with low heat, and throw in all the minor ingredients
# 姜蒜笋香菇 煸炒
Ginger, garlic, bamboo shoots and shiitake mushrooms. Stir fry them
# 黄酒
Some cooking wine
# 酱油
Soy sauce
# 这是借酱油的味 你看
It’s for the extra layer of flavour
# 因为它有酱 有豆瓣酱
It already has the sauce, Dou Ban Jiang
# 咸度基本上差不多了
So it has enough salt in there
# 糖
Some sugar
# 看到没有 你看这汁黏不黏
Now you can see, is the sauce viscous?
# 烧出来以后就这样
It will look like this after braising
# 这干嘛 搁一点水
What’s next, pour in some water
# 有很多人做干烧都要勾芡
A lot of people add slurry when dry braising
# 这种是错误的 就不能勾芡
That’s wrong. You can’t add slurry
# 干烧是自然收汁 对
Dry braising is reducing the sauce down naturally. Yes
# 醋 三叔做菜醋的量是比较大的
Some Vinegar. San Shu, you always use generous amounts of vinegar in your dishes
# 我是拿的比较准的
I know the exact amount I need
# 给一点点盐 不给盐它不香
Season it with some salt, otherwise it won’t be as aromatic
# 看这颜色怎么样 可以
What do you think of the colour? Amazing
# 这个时候就把鱼下下去了
Now, bring the fish back in the sauce
# 川菜的特点是什么
What’s one of the characteristics of Sichuan Cuisine?
# 葱出锅搁
You sprinkle some spring onions after the cooking is done
# 那就是咱们这所说倒炝呗
This is what we call ‘reverse cooking’
# 倒炝 倒烹
Yes, reverse cooking
# 一定是甜辣咸酸 这叫干烧
When it has sweetness, spiciness, saltiness and sourness well mixed and combined, this is called a decent dry braising dish.
# 在家能烧一条好鱼来
To cook a delicious fish dish at home
# 得需要工夫
It takes time.
# 一是要工夫  需要心细
And attention to details
# 做完以后你有成就感
When it’s done, you will be rewarded with the sense of achievement
# 你像咱们做这么多年了
After so many years of being professional chefs like us
# 每次一道菜如果出来成品特别好
Every time we cook a fantastic dish
# 心里也舒服
We feel so accomplished
# 有很多人就不知道往里头放甜面酱
Many people don’t know the secret of adding Tian Mian Jiang
# 包括咱们炒回锅肉
When cooking Sichuan Cuisine including the double-cooked pork
# 都要给点甜面酱
We all need to add some Tian Mian Jiang
# 它出来那个酱 最后发稠
It makes the finished sauce viscous
# 收汁的时候它拿酱收汁
It helps with the sauce reduction
# 有酱香的气味
And it adds some aroma
# 你说这么多料搁进去能不好吃吗
It’s impossible to make the fish not tasty after you put in so many ingredients
# 南方人不理解
Southern people don’t understand
# 说你们炖条鱼四十分钟鲜味没了
They say all the umami in the fish would have gone after 40 minutes of braising
# 其实我们很鲜
In fact, it will be super umami
# 鱼鲜 原材料好 怎么做都好吃
When the fish and other ingredients are all fresh and in great quality, the dish will always come out tasty however way you cook it
# 多㸆一会 有锅盖
Braise it for some extra time. We have the lid
# 干烧鱼不能盖盖
You can’t use a lid when dry braising
# （一盖盖）鱼皮和肉脱开了
Otherwise, the fish skin would come off the flesh
# 显得特别没精神 懒呼呼的
The fish would look drowsy and lazy
# 这跟一宿没睡觉似的
It would look like it hadn’t slept all night
# 一定是敞开小火慢炖
So dry braising must be lid free on low heat
# 这知识点知道了吧 知道了
Remember this tip. Got it
# 这个鱼烧完以后
Once cooking is done
# 有醋香味没有醋酸味
The fish will have the aroma from the vinegar, but it won’t taste acidic
# 为什么那么早搁醋
That’s why we added the vinegar that early
# 这个油得比正常烧鱼要稍微厚一点
We use slightly more oil than we normally would when cooking a fish
# 就是经常讲么
There is a saying
# 中餐没有油不好吃
Chinese Cuisine wouldn’t taste as good without the oil
# 这待会要拌点米饭 神了
Mix it with some rice in a minute. That’s fantastic
# 你看现在能看出来了
Now you can see
# 这有粘稠度没有 哪来的
Is there viscosity in the sauce? Where does it come from?
# 这就是酱里边来的 对甜面酱
It comes from the Tian Mian Jiang
# 粘稠度开始收
It will become even more viscous
# 如果你要不搁甜面酱
If you didn’t add Tian Mian Jiang
# 它没有这么黏
It wouldn’t be as viscous
# 噗嗤噗嗤小火慢收
Reduce the sauce down with very low heat
# 你像这火都属于大
The heat now is still too high for what is needed here
# 应该还小
It should turn down even lower
# 这鱼绝对到时候漂亮
This fish must be very beautiful once done
# 多棒这汁
How gorgeous is this sauce!
# 黏不黏 你勾什么芡啊
How viscous! No need of any slurry
# 这不是快速的东西
This is not fast food
# 烧就有过程的
Braising takes time
# 老饭骨做饭一定不能含糊
Lao Fan Gu always take cooking very seriously
# 真家伙摆出来
We show you the real deal
# 你看现在基本上差不多了
Now, it’s getting there
# 收的还是可以的吧
The sauce is perfectly reduced
# 咱们现在就可以出锅了
We can take it out of the wok now
# 最后炝葱花
Lastly, sprinkle some spring onions
# 咱们灭火
Heat off
# 不破其型
Don’t break the fish
# 老饭骨还是那句话
It’s still that saying from Lao Fan Gu
# 做菜就不能马虎 就不能含糊
Cooking is serious, you can’t cut corner
# 一定要有油
There must be some oil
# 这道菜我一定要学会
I need to learn this dish
# 做出来要有味道 层次感要强
The dish must have the layers and complexity of flavours
# import ending.srt 00:07:01,000 请原样保留此行